<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</title>
    <link>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.bacpop.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mutation Spectra in Streptococcus pneumoniae</title>
      <link>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/mutspect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/mutspect/</guid>
      <description>An Introduction to Mutation Spectra Mutational Spectra in Pneumococcal Epidemiology Conclusion An Introduction to Mutation Spectra It is intutitive that an organism&amp;rsquo;s ecological, phenotypic, or epidemiological context exposes it to distinct mutagens, and might thus produce specific signatures and patterns of mutation &amp;ndash; that organism&amp;rsquo;s mutational spectrum.
This idea is well-established in oncology. Cancer epidemiolgy studies have shown that a handful of genes, most prominently the human p53 gene, show patterns of mutation specific to the corresponding cancer types.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peer Review of the pre-print &#39;Endonuclease fingerprint indicates a synthetic origin of SARS-CoV-2&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/synthetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 13:22:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/synthetic/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Constructing the null distribution Comparing observations to the null distributions How do new restriction site locations emerge naturally? Mutation analysis Conclusion This is a peer review of the pre-print “Endonuclease fingerprint indicates a synthetic origin of SARS-CoV2”, it is highly recommended that you go and read the pre-print in order to understand this review.
Introduction The broad thread of the argument in the pre-print is that a synthetically engineered COVID-19 virus would be created using a process where ‘restriction’ enzymes cut the vaccine genome into roughly equal fragments so that they can be cloned in a bacterial system before being reassembled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualising microbial population structure with mandrake</title>
      <link>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/mandrake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bacpop.org/blog/mandrake/</guid>
      <description>Paper: https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2021.0237
(Joint work with Gerry Tonkin-Hill)
Dimensional reduction and embeddings Our work &amp;ndash; mandrake Running on genome datasets –- clusters at multiple resolutions Give it a go! Links What’s the bacronym? Dimensional reduction and embeddings Dimension reduction methods are a popular way to understand large amounts of genetic data: PCA, t-SNE and UMAP have all been used to analyse and visualise large numbers of samples in two-dimensions (with the latter being particularly popular with single cell techniques).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
