<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 15:20:11 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ggCaller installation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ggcaller_installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 15:20:11 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ggcaller_installation/</guid>
      <description>Installing ggCaller from Source Installing ggCaller with Docker More information about ggCaller Prerequisites&#xA;Before you begin, make sure your system meets the following requirements:&#xA;Operating System: Linux (recommended) or macOS. Compiler: GCC (GNU Compiler Collection) version 4.8 or higher. CMake: Version 3.1.0 or later. Git: Version 2.0 or later. Python: Version 3.6 or later. Pip: Python package installer. Basic familiarity with the command line interface. Please download the example fasta files from this link.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple horses for multiple courses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/horses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/horses/</guid>
      <description>This post is about a talk I gave in February 2020 at RSLondonSouthEast, a local conference for research software engineers. First an overview of the talk, then an update after following my own advice for the past few years.&#xA;Multiple horses for multiple courses Choosing a language When deciding which programming language to use for a project, a useful principle is &amp;lsquo;horses for courses&amp;rsquo; i.e. pick the one that is best suited for the task.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph-based gene prediction with ggCaller</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ggcaller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ggcaller/</guid>
      <description>The bacterial pangenome – quantifying within-species diversity How do you represent a pangenome? Our work – ggCaller How does ggCaller compare to existing tools? Check out the code and the paper In this blog, I give a brief overview of bacterial pangenome analysis, and what problems our tool, ggCaller, solves.&#xA;The bacterial pangenome – quantifying within-species diversity A genome is a set of biological instructions, known as ‘genes’, which describe how to make and maintain a living organism.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review: Wellcome Ideathon 2023</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ideathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ideathon/</guid>
      <description>The format Our Project (Student Team) Our Experience We attended the Wellcome Data Science Ideathon as semi-finalists in July 2023, which saw the Wellcome Trust invite around 100 researchers across 25 teams to compete to answer some of the biggest public health challenges we face today.&#xA;The format The Ideathon was similar to a Hackathon; groups were tasked with answering specific questions in one of three themes - Infectious Disease, Climate &amp;amp; Health, and Mental Health.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMBL-UNESCO Residency in Infection Biology Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/unesco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/unesco/</guid>
      <description>This application is now closed EMBL and UNESCO have recently announced a visitor programme as part of its infection biology scheme, in which we are participating (along with many other EMBL groups, see the link at the end for a full list).&#xA;Our group is participating in the scheme, and we&amp;rsquo;d be love to hear from interested candidates who would like to work with us. We have particular expertise in analysing genomic data from bacterial pathogens, developing and using new bioinformatic tools to do so, as well as developing mathematical models for pathogen transmission and evolution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutation Spectra in Streptococcus pneumoniae</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/mutspect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/mutspect/</guid>
      <description>An Introduction to Mutation Spectra Mutational Spectra in Pneumococcal Epidemiology Conclusion An Introduction to Mutation Spectra It is intutitive that an organism&amp;rsquo;s ecological, phenotypic, or epidemiological context exposes it to distinct mutagens, and might thus produce specific signatures and patterns of mutation &amp;ndash; that organism&amp;rsquo;s mutational spectrum.&#xA;This idea is well-established in oncology. Cancer epidemiolgy studies have shown that a handful of genes, most prominently the human p53 gene, show patterns of mutation specific to the corresponding cancer types.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Peer Review of the pre-print &#39;Endonuclease fingerprint indicates a synthetic origin of SARS-CoV-2&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/synthetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 13:22:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/synthetic/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Constructing the null distribution Comparing observations to the null distributions How do new restriction site locations emerge naturally? Mutation analysis Conclusion This is a peer review of the pre-print “Endonuclease fingerprint indicates a synthetic origin of SARS-CoV2”, it is highly recommended that you go and read the pre-print in order to understand this review.&#xA;Introduction The broad thread of the argument in the pre-print is that a synthetically engineered COVID-19 virus would be created using a process where ‘restriction’ enzymes cut the vaccine genome into roughly equal fragments so that they can be cloned in a bacterial system before being reassembled.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualising microbial population structure with mandrake</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/mandrake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 17:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/mandrake/</guid>
      <description>Paper: https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2021.0237&#xA;(Joint work with Gerry Tonkin-Hill)&#xA;Dimensional reduction and embeddings Our work &amp;ndash; mandrake Running on genome datasets –- clusters at multiple resolutions Give it a go! Links What’s the bacronym? Dimensional reduction and embeddings Dimension reduction methods are a popular way to understand large amounts of genetic data: PCA, t-SNE and UMAP have all been used to analyse and visualise large numbers of samples in two-dimensions (with the latter being particularly popular with single cell techniques).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
