<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Guides on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/guides/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Guides on Pathogen Informatics and Modelling Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 16:22:28 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/guides/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Building trees with SKA</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guides/building_trees_with_ska/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 16:22:28 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guides/building_trees_with_ska/</guid>
      <description>SKA is a tool for comparing small and highly similar genomes using split k-mers. This guide will explain how to use SKA to build a phylogenetic tree for different Escherichia coli lineages in a few minutes. Although SKA is tailored more towards analysing variation within a lineage, tree-building ends up working fine for the whole species but requires more memory.&#xA;Why SKA is good for building phylogenetic trees The basic approach to building a tree with SKA is to generate a SNP alignment using split k-mers and then feed that to a tree building algorithm of choice.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A beginner&#39;s guide to fitting PopPUNK models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/guides/poppunk_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 12:12:42 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/guides/poppunk_models/</guid>
      <description>PopPUNK now has a lot of different models available, which can make it hard to know where to start, or to tell if you&amp;rsquo;ve done the right thing when fitting one to your data.&#xA;Some questions I&amp;rsquo;ll address:&#xA;Do you need to fit a new model? Should I subsample my data? Which model should I use? Are my clusters correct? My clusters don&amp;rsquo;t match MLST/CC tl;dr&#xA;Don&amp;rsquo;t fit a model if you don&amp;rsquo;t have to.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
